How does the other side of you, if at all, does it show up when either you're deep in a script
and you feel like that creative slice show up? Or when you're in the middle of, you know,
a jazz performance and you feel like the structural, you know, kind of comes in? How
do those two interplay for you? I think that when you use the analogy of left side, right side brain,
that's not really what's going on. What's really going on is there's two different roles that you
assume, Observer and participant. If we think of it that way, then it's pertinent to everything.
On today's episode of The Pro Guide, Wired Magazine calls him the Dean of Automation.
He served as Product Manager for Automation Technologies for Apple for over 20 years,
Sal Seguyan. Today's episode of The Pro Guide is brought to you by Small Pond Productions,
the producers of this podcast. If you're looking to boost your Brand's voice with professional
and podcast production. Whether it's an interview show or telling stories with audio,
we walk you through every step of the process to make you sound great. Head to our website
and download the free Podcasting Made Simple Guide. Eight critical things you need to know
before launching your Brand's podcast. It's all available at smallpond.productions.
Well, welcome everybody to this episode of The Pro Guide. My name's Andrew J. Mason,
Andrew today we're talking to Sal Segoian. He's the automation technology product manager for
20 years. Wired Magazine calls him the Dean of Automation. He's a musician with a love for piano
and guitar. He has two albums available for purchase on Apple Music under the band name
Blue Indigo, Catwalk, and To Be With You. And he also happens to be a self-taught programmer. We
get into some really cool questions and answers about right brain, left brain, logic, creativity,
interplay, and a lot of Sal's history that maybe you haven't heard yet so far. So I hope you enjoy
this interview with South Segoin. Talk to me about this journey of self-teaching AppleScript
and you kind of hit on it a little bit before we hit record, but I want to kind of dip back
into that too. And how did you end up on this path of AppleScript? My gosh.
AppleScript and I met each other totally by mistake on a whim.
um i used to live in a music Community an Arts community in Pennsylvania called Delaware Water
Gap that's the actual name of the town because you're right on the Delaware River where the Gap
is coming in between the mountains and it's in the Poconos and and it's a very famous Arts and
Music community and it has been for decades and decades and i was living over a bar
in there and i bought a a used Mac and uh i taught myself i mean i was basically you know
they're pressing it trying to figure it out i had no instruction or anything about it
and I i got a program called Ready Set Go which was a page layout program right the early stages
of page line there was either page maker or Ready set go and i i got ready set go and i taught myself
how to use it and i started making the menus for the bar right first thing I'm going to do is like
oh man take these old menus and i redid them you know and i learned about kerning and fonts and
and printed them out on a laser writer.
I had a laser writer and everything.
And the next thing I know, the other businesses around town
beside the bar I was living at started to ask me,
can you do my thing over again?
You know, the little video shop and the diner,
the Greek diner down the street.
And so I started doing this.
I went, wait a minute.
There's something going on here.
Yeah.
And it appealed to me because it was, you know, dealing with logic and and creativity and all those kind of things.
And I got pretty good at it. I moved to Charlottesville, Virginia, where I had lived before I had gone to the University of Virginia at one time.
And I got a job in a Print Service Bureau with this lady, Joe Gibson.
she had been in the print industry for 29 30 years and she taught me all the the real stuff
you know about line letting and all those kind of things but this was at the time of uh desktop
publishing was just starting to become a concept and we were getting in all these print jobs
because we had a line at tronic and i was constantly looking for new ways to do things
and automate things because when you got all these jobs coming in flight checking them all
is a pain and so i was working with developers of Quark extensions and I'm coming up with these
ideas and testing them for them and i happen to have this thing from Apple developer magazine
and it said apple script this english-like language that can control the actions of the
computer and the applications and I'm like huh so i i got the dvd you know or the cd or whatever it
was on and I'm sitting there it's late at night it's like after 11 o'clock at night or something
I'm sitting there and I'm trying to figure this out it says okay applications have dictionaries
and you should be able to write this sentence in this application called Script editor and run this
sentence and it should be able to control while i was using Quark Express was one of the apps we
were using in publishing and it was scriptable because Dave Dave and Ralph Rich had worked
with Tim Gill and put the dictionary in there and i also used FileMaker Pro which had some scripting
support and you could get a scriptable finder i paid the fourteen dollars to get a 400k
uh disk with the scriptable finder on it from Apple and so the first script i ever wrote was
for Quark Express and it was this set the color of the current box to Blue and so i wrote that
script and i read it and the box turned blue and i went oh okay all of a sudden everything in my
whole life just changed i like fired all my design clients i just worked constantly i lived in that
room for like months figuring this out like what is this because all of a sudden i had the power
to control the machine i didn't have to go to the developer i was working with and said you know
it'd be nice if it did this yes or can you make it do blah i mean there were great people to work
you know like uh you know some of the companies i was working with uh were really great and
interesting people to work with but this is mine that's right i could control this and so i started
working on it and with a bent towards you know design and publication because i was working in
a Print Service Bureau first thing i started doing was trying to figure out how to automate
real estate Publications because you know in the in the grocery stores they had these magazines with
house description house description house description you know that kind of stuff
and I'm looking at it going well that could just be a record in a FileMaker Pro database
and then this is a box so all I have to do is figure out some way to relate that box to this
well I could use the mls number and I'll put the mls number in a field over here and then I'll tag
the box with it because you could tag boxes and so i figured out how to write an apple script to
get the information from the database into the box and format it and started coming up with it and
then you know i explored that and i was able to do an entire page layout in 20 seconds and it was
accurate it wasn't any mistakes and i was like whoa okay so i started working on that
and then i got into well why can't we take images why do i have to like do all these half tones and
stuff it says i can scan it let me try this and sure enough it started working the local Real
Estate Group in in the county came to me and we started doing their real estate publication and
automated their cover. I did the first three colors. I mean,
full color cover that was split electronically, you know, all that.
And, uh, I started, uh, you know,
gaining a reputation and I was writing scripts for companies.
I got contacted by AT&T. AT&T says, can you write us a script?
We got 40 page documents and we have to find every occurrence of AT&T.
it has to be this blue it has to be this font turn this way with this and i said no problem
that'll be three thousand bucks and you know I'll write it in 10 minutes and then sit on it for a
week before i send it to him to make them think i worked on it now i said right yeah and i started
getting a reputation and i wrote i wrote the script for Better Homes and Gardens that did
the fractions for their recipes all this kind of stuff and i started developing this whole thing
and then i got queries from magazines can you write an article about this can you tell people
what you're doing I started writing magazine articles on automation with you know Apple
script and then i started getting asked to to speak at shows so i i you know i had a collection
of scripts i was selling to extension this this company that sold Quark extensions and i was
selling these Scripts and i would speak at shows and then Apple i noticed that my audience was
Apple Apple they would stand there and they'd like and they came to me and they said we want
you to join and i go well why would i want to do that you know you're asking me to take a 50
percent pay cut to join you you know and they basically threatened to kill the baby right they
said well Apple script's gonna die unless you come here and it was a basically a scheme by
shafas i had Chris Espinoza bom and Dara and you know a bunch of people to get me on board
And I joined Apple in January of 97 as the AppleScript product manager.
And at that time, it was like the Poseidon Adventure you know, where the columns were falling down and Shelley Winters was doing the breaststroke through the hallway, you know.
It was Insanity
it was really crazy but that was the best possible thing for me because it meant that all the
barriers were down and we could actually take a vision and move forward with it that's how i got
started with the whole thing yeah this uh this isn't on my list i first of all i love that little
detail about the them coming to you with a knife up to Apple script saying i swear I'll do it
basically yeah don't make me do this um but i i do appreciate uh when you talk about the vision
for what it could be what what did that look like to you for Apple script you know you have in your
mind uh they say you know everything's on the table it's all available and it's up to you know
you have this vision for where you think it could go what were you picturing when when that was
happening well one of the things that I've I've just had as part of my life i think you know was
taught to me by my father was to look for the underlying principle behind something
you see something working and you would look at it and go why is that doing what it does
why is it having that effect let's look behind here and figure this out you know why does the
clock do this why does the drawer come out like that and the underlying principle behind Apple
script was this empowerment that you could have access to the apis of the operating system
or the applications in a way that wasn't so complex that you had to write code and compile
and do all those kind of things so if you got that concept then you want to have it apply to
everything but what happened is is when i joined Apple it was really more of a rather than a
technological challenge it was more of a political challenge because at that time apple script was
not part of the operating system. We're talking like System 7, right? Before System 8. I got there
just before System 8. System 8 was the first one that I was involved in. And it was not part of
the operating system. It was an extra that you got that you had to buy. And so I soon discovered that
the way that Apple work is, you know, if you have a technology, you have something and it doesn't
it, then it can die quickly. You know, you need somebody like a member of Congress to represent
that technology and to protect it and to make the deals necessary to advance it forward.
So the first challenge I had with AppleScript when I got there was just keeping it alive.
You know, AppleScript and the concept of automation had many near-death experiences,
of my time in the early days was just involved in the practicality of making relationships and
and making deals and having knife fights in the hallway to get this thing to keep going
it wasn't that you know i didn't have the vision for okay everything should be scriptable and that
this is what you could do with it i saw what you could do with it because that's what i was doing
for a living but the Practical situation at the time was that it needed representation it needed
somebody to keep it alive and so my challenge was constantly trying to get the resources and so
you know at one time Apple script was put under color sync they didn't know what to do with it so
they assign i reported to the color sync product manager it was like what it took forever and all
kinds of stuff and then you know it was massive shake-ups and one day i lost uh my boss's boss
my boss my uh uh companion my my peers lost them all in one day it was just like total clear house
and I was left and it was like and people were coming to me with their projects saying can you
keep this alive you know and give me the source code for their projects and like data detectors
you know they gave me their stuff trying to keep it alive it was very challenging in those days
but at the same time in that challenge in that period of of turmoil all these opportunities
there was no there was no layers of blocking if i needed to if i had a concept that something
needed to be scriptable I'd find out who in the os is working on that and i'd go over to his office
or her office right and i show them what i was doing and say look if we do this and connect this
to this then all of this is possible and it was like okay open up the code change that right there
yeah, that makes a difference. Let's put it in, submit it. You know,
then it became a challenge of trying to figure out how to get stuff past Kim
COVID, you know, who was like the guardian of the code.
And, uh, when I would walk in the room, they'd be like, okay,
what are you doing here?
Because I had been caught many times with my hand in the cookie jar,
trying to get stuff in the door. Right. And, uh,
so fortunately for me i got to work with a brilliant one of the most brilliant people
i ever met at apple and a wonderful human being as Chris says Chris Espinoza Apple employee number
eight was my engineering counterpart and uh he Chris was just fantastic to work with
you know he had done he had been there since it was in the garage wow and yeah Chris's is
he's like one of the original guys and and uh the challenge you know he bait he he and uh uh
the QuickTime product manager at the time uh kidnapped the code base and basically he took
it off the server and had it and they brought me on board to protect it and he made a deal with
Steve glass to get apple script to become part of the operating system so we can be protected but at
had to give up our autonomy so we couldn't just rev when we wanted to we couldn't do what we wanted
to we had to go through the system processes but Steve protected us you know Steve glass protected
us so that's the first challenge is we had to get into into the operating system and then at the
same time Apple had let go a lot of the guys like uh John Pew and don Olson that were part now of
the AppleScript team had been absorbed by them and they let them all go. And I remember that day
when they all went out the door and, you know, I'm watching my heroes and these people that I've
admired for years just leave and get picked up by Adobe and everybody else. So it was a challenging
time, but it enabled me to make the relationships and the political structures so that it could get
in place and then Steve came and uh my relationship with Steve was definitely
one of the reasons i think that it survived uh the first time Steve and i met was in town hall
in front of about i don't know 80 people all product marketing Steve called us in there and
he was ranting about how we sucked and how we couldn't Market our way out of a paper bag and
how it was uh easy when we were a hundred times better than Windows but now that we're not you
don't know what to do and the first words i said to Steve i stopped him i said no you're wrong
and he turns around he looks at me and he goes and you are i said I'm also going on the Apple
script product manager you're wrong my technology is 100 times better than Windows and we just went
at it you know we just locked horns and went you know Steve says well that's not what I'm hearing
and I'm said your guys are lying to you you know they're not telling you the truth he goes well
they say that nobody's using i said everybody's using this what are you talking about
half our procedures are built on this stuff you know and uh it that was like the beginning of
my relationship with Steve he understood that i would tell him the truth and that what i
taught would tell him i had backed up i knew this was reality and so there was numerous times uh
that i went to him and it made a difference that we got the resources we needed like uh when we
wanted one of the challenges we had was we wanted to become part of the development environment
but we weren't we were just like the scripting language off to the side and everything else was
this objective c and c plus plus and i had known i had a friend that was vice president over in
marketing or something and he had uh ridden in the plane with Steve from New York from a Mac world
and he and he told me about the conversation some of the conversations they had he told me
Steve's favorite movie he said Steve's favorite movie is Patton he won't believe it but it's
patent and i went well it kind of makes sense right and so uh i i you know i came from a
military family so I know how to speak military so i wrote Steve an email i said Steve look I'm just
a sergeant I'll do what you tell me I'll go where you go want me to go I'll fight the fight you know
i said but you got me out here in the middle of nowhere with no supply line how am i supposed to
take it to Microsoft if i don't have the stuff that i need to you know get ahead that's right
and i sent it off to him it was like the middle of the night you know like midnight complete
military metaphor total it's like I'm a dutiful Soldier I'll do what you tell me to do but you
know you got me out here in the middle of nowhere next day i get a call from Espinoza going what
did you do i said what do you mean he goes what did you do we got a meeting today with Avi and
Phil and so i said well i sent this letter to Steve so the next day we go in to see Abby and
and phil and he said what do you need you know what do you want to do do you really want to take
this i said no man we got this great technology we need to take it to them and what do you need
and they said well what do you need to take it to them do you want to buy like a third party that's
already got some kind of interface thing or what do you want to do and Espinosa says no we want to
be part of project Builder and interface Builder and avi had been sitting there kind of like i got
to do this and went oh you know i can understand that he goes yeah we want to be a peer development
language and they went hmm okay how you know what do you need and and Espinoza goes one engineer
he goes what he goes we need Tim bumgarner and it was this brilliant man who could architect the
thing and figure it out and so he goes you got him and that changed everything because then we
became a development language we could actually make an app out of apple script using aqua and
everything else and that all happened because of my relationship with Steve i love you know and
time there was you know times it's that sj would referee like fights between me and other guys
trying to get them scriptable like i lost the fight with Final Cut i was getting calls from
cnn and everybody else all the time about they needed automation i had worked on an automation
for Viacom my friend Dirk van dole was a bb over there and i had spent like a couple weeks on site
their media using media 100 was an application that was scriptable the mac and we automated the
creation of all those their promos you know those little things that go tomorrow on you know fx
channel we have Bob discovers America you know and it would have like a certain video background
with over overlay text and things and and uh it turned out that the guy that was recording those
and they would do them all in one take and he would sit there and just read one after another
with 10 second intervals in between so i wrote a script it would hack all that up take those put
them on a thing figure out what based upon the name what of the 13 channels that they had pull
of the appropriate video background put it in create open up Photoshop and illustrator and
create all the text overlay put it in there with an alpha Channel build the entire thing lay them
all out on one line and then somebody would sit there and scrub through to make sure they're all
correct then another script would cut them all into sections send them high res up to the media
surfer and a low res over to where the execs could review it from a web page all built with apple
script right wow so i was trying to get the final cut guys to do this and uh
i couldn't convince the engineers that they needed to spend the time and do it
oh my gosh was the kind of thing you want to do when you're writing the code re-architecting it
later is a pain right it's really hard and i was trying to convince them and i couldn't make
progress so i i pulled a move on them and Steve it turned out too i used to speak at the executive
briefing Center and i knew that uh hbo and a bunch of the guys from New York were showing up
so i asked Viacom i said hey can i show your solution to your competitors and they're like
okay yeah you know they're they're doing like all of a sudden they're doing 1800 of these things
that used to take like weeks with four guys back to back they're doing in like 30 minutes with a
bunch of scripts oh my gosh yes so i i got into the the queue of people that were going to show
those things i was the last one and i showed him i said look at Viacom said i could show you this
and then all of a sudden everybody's like what and i showed them and they're just their faces went
like pong sure and then after me i left after me was sj and Steve came in and the first thing
this guy said to him were we want automation we want what we just and he didn't know anything
so i basically set him up to get bombarded right thinking okay I'll get them asking for it
maybe that'll give me some leverage that's a brilliant move I love it it turned out didn't
work you know and in the NSJ said look at I got to go with the engineering manager they say they
don't have the time and the resources we're way behind on this I'm sorry we can't do this I was
like okay I tried you know that was my attitude some things you know like automator Steve got
and he made it part of the operating system but sometimes I lost as well but it was basically
because that relationship with him allowed us to get the resources to keep moving automation
forward and we did you know Apple script we got over to the power pc it you know we kept making
advances with it all along the way you know then it became apple script Objective c Chris Neville
that and it just blew everything away because then you could call into all the Coco Frameworks
directly but when Steve died you know we lost a really valuable Ally and the company changed and
it became a lot of stove piping and my previous thing of having horizontal relationships between
groups to keep automation as a primary mover hit walls yeah and you know it was more difficult to
effective in those days around that situation so that's a long answer to your question about
Apple script but that's basically what it was about yeah i love every minute that that's awesome
and the uh the of the Via story that's fantastic uh i i would love to jump into
this intersection that you had uh of music and in particular Jazz and technology and and for you
sounds like music was kind of the groundwork the framework that came first and out of that or
alongside of that later was developed this uh you know the this the scripting and the aha moment
with the uh the blue box you know and quark and everything yeah talk to me about how you might
think that one of those disciplines or areas might inform the others and if there's any
any or what that relationship might look like for you there's a
a lot of similarities there's basic principles that I've found throughout my life that are
relevant that are constant across uh knowledge bases that are that are constant across Technologies
you know there are certain things that are just basic truths that pertain to all of them
for example you know you looking for the underlying principle when it comes to if
you're dealing with music you know what's the underlying principle behind what you're doing
uh why does why does a set of chords sound it's feel a certain way why does this type of resolve
happen here you know you look for the underlying principle behind something in the same way
as you know why a clock mechanism Works a certain way and once you understand the underlying
principle behind something then you can replicate that and you can build upon it and take it forward
But if you're just working with what's on the outside, then you don't have the depth and the understanding to move it forward.
Whether that's music or whether it's automation technology, the principle is the same.
What's the underlying principle?
And it's basically empowerment.
You know, the fact that the you know, automation is basically some type of messaging system where you're telling applications what they should be doing and the user is directing the movement and the control.
And once you understand that, then you just figure out the technology that's necessary for that particular application becomes more apparent.
There's also things about in order to succeed, it was a lot of the time, like I mentioned, it was political initially until it became something that was more ingrained and accepted as being part of that whole environment.
And that depended a lot upon personal insight and personal belief in yourself, you know, being okay with what you know and being okay with the concept of challenging the status quo, you know, moving what it takes to get the goal, you know, within reason.
but you have to try to figure out that everything that God done
was really personal relationships.
And I became notorious for certain kind of things.
Like I was famous for putting bounties on code.
I would put a bounty up in the elevator, $1,200,
for somebody that can write me code that does blah.
like uh the uh QuickTime QuickTime Player to get that scriptable was a bounty in the elevator and
building too pardon me or somebody could write me code and with about 30 minutes i got a couple
calls from guys are this serious i said yeah I'll give you 1200 in cash if you write me code to do
a player and here's what it has to do and they would write me that somebody wrote me the code
and uh then i said you know okay strip it take out you take out your identifiers your job numbers
everything i said just give me the code and then once i had that was figuring out how to get it in
you know making a deal with somebody else to put this in here or install it into there uh there was
a lot of things in the operating system like the number one used apple script command is called do
shell script well i purchased that there was a guy i i bought the code for that from and it took me a
while to figure out how to get it into the operating system but it got slid into a build you know and
once it was in there it became used by everybody and it's still like one of the most number one
use things but it was basically a bounty i paid some engineer and then there were certain guys
that wouldn't accept money so i used uh Legos the famous Star Wars Millennium Falcon i used to buy
the Millennium Falcon kits and i would come into an engineer and I'd put it on his desk and they'd
look at it like oh my this is something that they can't justify their wife spending 500
Millennium Falcon kit but you know it's like you just give me the code I'll take care of the rest
of it and there was a lot of things that needed to be done but that's just all process of
establishing uh the sensibility of it once people started seeing the practicality and the necessity
of automation then it took on a life of its own and got accepted but i had to be confident in who
in was and in order to risk that you know they could have fired me yeah but the way i looked at
it is you know they asked me to be there i i was trying to do the right thing and Advance the
Technologies and keep it going and moving it forward and you know if i had to kind of fudge
things here and there and make deals and that's just the way it was because then in the end the
right thing got done and the original work that was by all of these fantastic engineers and people
involved in that has been carried on and now it's ingrained and you you have the the automation
Frameworks that are so essential and they're part of all of Apple's stuff now they're not going to
go away there's no question about whether they're going to be there anymore and that's wonderful
because the people that are using it are just have that opportunity but it's all from basically
being confident in the rightness of what you were doing and trying to move it forward i i love um
two things I'll call out on that before we before we move forward and one is is this sense where
uh humility and confidence they aren't necessarily diametrically opposed to each other you believe so
much you're so confident and it's coming from a place of authenticity but it's also this open
hand where you're talking about uh you know Viacom like hey i tried i did my best i did what i thought
was work and i wasn't you know tight-fisted enough to where it's like i have to have my way
yeah the other slice i love about this is um is how not myopic it is too you know so many of us
if we're into code or programming and that's our thing we think about our one job our one role
and this is like really zooming out saying okay let's begin with the end in mind here what are
we really all here trying to accomplish and these alternate approaches like the millennial
fountain or about you know code bounty um i love it yeah it's
there's a truth about automation you know the truth the power of the computer should reside
in the hands of the one using it that's been a core fundamental Creed for me and that's a truth
that you know i just followed that's my belief and that's what i was pushing for at Apple the
whole time i was there almost 20 years and when you know that to be true and it's so empowering
and you see that it changes people's lives literally changes people's lives for the better
you know it's it becomes easier to become a champion for it and to push it because it's
the right thing that's right it's then it just becomes a matter of you know trying to solve
problems like we had to work with the security guys Yvonne christic's team and yeah basically
two diametrically opposed philosophies automation wants everything wide open and the security team
wants everything you know tight and those guys are so brilliant and their attitude
was constantly how do we make this work and working with them was just fantastic and we
figured out this whole concept that's still in use today that if the user installs this at a
certain place that the operating system will run your scripts and the act of the user installing
it means that the user wants us to have power of the user that the application can't install it
but the application can ask the user to install it so you know you have this engine the script
engine the i don't know how they're doing it now in the latest builds was basically like there was
a script engine that would run apple script and shell scripts for you the system would do it and
certain locations to have them approved right and that resolution between the two teams was
brilliant and it's still working today but it didn't happen on iOS iOS you know that's
unfortunately there was this political situation where there was like different teams in different
buildings that weren't allowed to communicate with each other and you couldn't you know make
the relationships there was you know idea barrier doors glass doors that would separate you and they
didn't take it on we we approached the ios team numerous times with basically the concept behind
what shortcuts is today back then but they didn't want it so they hard-coded everything and uh it
got in a mess. And now you have this wonderful architecture on Mac
but it's not duplicated on iOS. I mean,
one of the things that I wish could have happened would be that
there would have been a universal scripting language for all of Apple's
products. So that it would be,
you write the script once and it goes everywhere.
Like what I've been working with the Omni group Yes.
Omni group uses JavaScript based on webkit core JavaScript so that you write a script for an omni
application whether it's running on your phone or your ipad or your Mac it's going to run the same
and it's everywhere it's it's device independent that was always my goal for apple and unfortunately
that didn't happen uh there was also another goal that we were trying to get to i work with
many years I worked with the speech team and then the Siri team came on and i worked with them
and we actually had the prototyping engine for Siri they had this engine based on JavaScript
we had it tied into apple script and to Apple events and there was like we had as a prototype
hundreds of Commands to control all the eye work apps photos the finder everything it was all voice
and it was natural language you didn't have to memorize a phrase it was just you tell it what
you wanted to do and it understood and we presented this all the way up to the top levels and people
were stunned literally I I gave presentations on this with my partner from the Siri team
the leap and uh the room was silent and then it Applause it was just like knocked the breath out
of them because we were doing this with Siri but the problem was that it was on the Mac it wasn't
it on ios and i think that caused problems because they didn't want ios to look bad not bad but not
as capable right yeah and one of the things i learned in working with Steve was i used to think
of it this way it's not my job to make you look good it's my job to push the envelope
and i come up with a solution that just keeps pushing it you know early on when i when he came
back on board there was a meeting in the boardroom some reason i was called into it Steve called a
bunch of the product managers and people into the the boardroom over in building one and I'm you know
and he he basically laid it out that we had to out innovate out maneuver out deliver
everybody else all of our competition that that's how we win is we just have to keep pushing the
envelope and uh he had a direction to go that he he had in mind and so the the trick was aligning
to do with that direction too but it was the whole thing keep pushing the envelope and i wasn't really
concerned that you know would make the the work that we had with Automation and Siri
would make uh another group look bad we just wanted to keep pushing the envelope so i actually
gave a a talk at wwdc about i used the standard dictation software as an example i didn't show
but i showed this whole thing and it it upset a lot of people they actually pulled the session
it was session 717 2016 and i gave the session and then they took down the videos like a week
later wow wow but you just have to keep pushing you know sometimes you win sometimes you don't
Yeah, I love for you to talk to me about this, this kind of back and forth that's maybe it is just integrated, you know, however you'd like to approach it. But this right brain, left brain, you know, the musical side and and the side that that is, you know, logical and code functioning.
how does the other side of you if at all does it show up when either you're deep in a script and
you feel like that that kind of creative slice show up or when you're in the middle of you know
a jazz performance and you feel like the the structural you know kind of comes in how do
those two interplay for you it's uh i think that when you use the analogy of left side right side
brain that's not really what's going on what's really going on is there's two different roles
that you assume Observer and participant if we think of it that way then it's pertinent to
everything they for example if you take a musician like Phil Woods you know when i lived in the
Poconos Phil was a local guy and uh amazing musician just phenomenal you know constantly
voted like best Alto player in the world but if you take Phil and he's playing in a group
and you could stop go if you could say Phil stop and then ask him okay what's going on right now
Phil could tell you everything that he was doing, the Ark of where he was going, what's happening,
who's playing what over here, what the bass note is, what's the harmony back here. He could tell
you exactly everything that was going on at that moment, but that's the Observer side.
At the same time, he was the participant. The creative flow of ideas and his response to
of all of the things that are going on with the rest of the group and his natural inspiration
is allowed to come out at the same time. You assume a role of both participant and observer.
And this pertains to anything that you do. It can be with a conversation with another person.
By being both participant and observer, you can correct and adjust for mistakes that you make because you can see you're observing the result of the impact of what you're saying on this person, but at the same time, you're going, oh, that was a mistake.
I'm sorry.
You know, that was not right.
I should have said this.
I didn't mean that.
Whatever.
It gives you the chance to correct.
Participant and observer, it works with everything.
It's the creative and it's the observant and the rational, all that stuff, but if you really
think of it in roles, it works with everything that you do in life.
And that's important because I think the Saving Grace that we have as human beings is the
in Forward Motion i call it Forward Motion we're constantly moving forward we can't go backwards
right you can't go back in time and correct that bad note ah i played the wrong you can't go back
but you can recognize that and you can develop a tool like okay let's think of it this way
I'm in the river I'm in a river that's moving and the current's moving i can't go back Upstream
strong right but i have a paddle and i can recognize that there's a rock coming up and i
can turn the paddle to get me to move to the little just to the left of it or a Craig in the
coming out of the water some Branch or something i can make adjustments having Forward Motion gives
us the ability to adjust to correct mistakes to correct deficiencies to correct defects of
whatever, right? And that also applies to everything else you're doing. And in order
to make that work, you have to be the guy steering, but at the same time, you got to
be the guy looking. So you have to be Observer and participant in everything that you do.
And that's what musicians do. That's what great artists do, that they observe and they
participate at the same time. When you're writing code, it happens the same kind of way too. You're
both Observer and participant of what's going on. And so I like to think of it in terms of that
rather than I'm using this side of my brain or that side of the brain. You know, you try to
maintain that balance between Observer and participant so that you don't go too far into
one and not the other that's what i look at oh my gosh does that make sense it does uh you just said
that phrase uh Forward Motion you know I'm thinking about that now as you're talking and uh
and you mentioned too it can happen in conversations too so i guess the Observer
is starting to think about that so um in in your life you know you've had some really great
wonderful Forward Motion that's happened and as that Arc continues to move forward uh what else
would you love to see show up for you and this is super open-ended it can be career it can be
life you know it could be anything but uh what else in the in the realm of Forward Motion would
you like to see happen for south segoi well i think that we're all at an incredible moment
in the history of mankind right now.
You know, it's obvious to anybody that's paying attention
that we are at an inflection moment in history
like none other that we've ever faced.
The whole thing going on with climate, you know,
it's been my experience that if you're a person
that requires pain to learn something,
will be provided to you in the amount required that you know if i really if that's the way i
learned by doing that then you'll get what you need yeah and I'm seeing that principle applied
to the World At Large that all of society is now becoming aware we're getting levels of pain
that are making us aware and having to respond and that means we're going to do fundamental
changes in the way that we that we perceive that we represent that we have government that we do
economy everything's going to be happening i i see that as incredible disturbance kind of thing
but at the same time it's been my experience like i was describing when i was at Apple and
this whole turmoil that was the time that the the solutions were born and and begun to be integrated
and i think that's going to happen now i think that the the world's going to be facing things
where the solutions are going to be coming up the creative the creativity the technology the
people the determination the character all of those things are going to be called to the fore
we have to think about well what's my place where do i fit in this and how's this going to affect me
but also at the same time how am i going to be involved in it you know
it's all about the timing and this is our time in the world and so i i see as scary as it is
it do get hope in what i see some of the things that are happening with people some people are
very passionate about it and some of the solutions we're coming up with are really incredible and
amazing and i have hope that Humanity can respond at the same time i understand it's going to be
very painful process that we're going to go through because the world that we know is never
going to be the same you know I'm never going to have a need for a sled when i was a kid there used
to be snow on the ground and you would buy every kid had like a beat up sled that we used to take
and stuff and then it stopped snowing and there's no more of that so things are going to change
but I think out of it it gives us the opportunity to become tighter and more understanding and more
empathetic and to figure out Solutions together it's going to be challenging but i i think that's
what's happening and trying to figure out your own place in that is is interesting too every
one of us you as a father yeah have to be thinking about okay this is affecting my family hum what's
what's going to happen you know everybody's going to be involved in this somehow and it's together
that we're going to solve and come to some kind of of of solution it's not going to be changing it
back to what it was because that's gone now and it will take thousands of years to change it back
to come to a solution having an answer and we're going to do it together because that's just
the necessity of it and the pain of it will force us into that
so is that too heavy yes that's like just feel like with a Nerf valve like no i i would not
change a minute of this conversation i love every bit of it um and i i appreciate uh even with the
full realization uh from what i consider to be a very brilliant person of the magnitude of the
challenge that's ahead of us uh also the optimism that's tied in with you know what when you're you
change when you're forced to and uh it looks like we might be getting there sooner than later so
you're you're a uh glass person if you can learn from the mistakes of others
and there's been many times I've been able to learn from the mistakes of others and i i'm so
grateful for that you know i am a blessed human being the fact I'm still here and that i get to
contribute and make contributions in a variety of ways and that i have a wonderful partner to
share my life with I'm a blessed person and you know we will all do this together we'll figure
out how to Clump together in that River and keep going we'll make this happen that's right we will
succeed that's right so always an honor to talk to you thank you so much for this time and our
thanks to all of you for listening if you're looking for a quick way to make our Day a review
in itunes or subscribing to this podcast would mean the world to us our thanks to small pond
productions for sponsoring and this was the pro guide learn from leaders change your life see
You